Guide to the Darlene Clark Hine Papers, circa 1879-1996 and undated, bulk 1950-1996 RL.00546
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Darlene Clark Hine papers
circa 1879-1996, bulk 1950-1996 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Hine, Darlene Clark
RL.00546
24.6 Linear Feet
Darlene Clark Hine is an African American professor, historian, college administrator, and published author in the field of African American history.
9225 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Darlene Clark Hine Papers were partially processed by staff at Michigan State University, and received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2007.
Biographical Note
Chronology List
Feb. 7, 1947 Born Darlene Clark in Morley, Missouri, to Levester and Lottie Mae Clark
1968 B.A. in American History and English from Roosevelt University
1970 M.A. in American History from Kent State University. Married William C. Hine (1970-1974)
1972-1974 Assistant Professor of History and Coordinator of Black Studies at South Carolina State College
1974-1979 Assistant Professor at Purdue University
1975 Ph.D. in African American History from Kent State University
1978-1979 Interim Director of the Africana Studies and Research Center at Purdue University
1979-1985 Associate Professor at Purdue University
1979 Published Black Victory: The Rise and Fall of the White Primary in Texas
1980-1982 Co-Director, OAH/ABWH Black Women's History Project
1981 Published When the Truth is Told: A History of Black Women's Culture and Community in Indiana, 1875-1950
1981-1986 Appointed Vice-Provost, Purdue University
1984-1985 President, Southern Association for Women Historians
Jan.-May 1985 Visiting Distinguished Professor, Arizona State University
1985-1987 Professor of History, Purdue University
1986-1987 Founding Member and Director of Publications, Association of Black Women Historians (ABWH)
1987-2004 John A. Hannah Distinguished Professor of American History, Michigan State University
1989 Published Black Women in White: Racial Conflict and Cooperation in the Nursing Profession, 1890-1950
1989-1990 Visiting Distinguished Professor of Women's Studies, University of Delaware
1994 Published Hine Sight: Black Women and the Reconstruction of American History
1995 Published More Than Chattel: Black Women and Slavery in America, edited with David Berry Gasper
1996 Published Speak Truth to Power: Black Professional Class in United States History
Feb 1996 Robert McNair Visiting Professor of Southern Studies, University of South Carolina
Sept.-Dec. 1996 Harold Washington Visiting Professor, Roosevelt University
April-July 1997 Avalon Distinguished Visiting Professor, Northwestern University
2001-2002 President of the Organization of American Historians (OAH)
2002-2003 President of Southern Historical Association (SHA)
2003 Published new edition of Black Victory: The Rise and Fall of the White Primary in Texas
2004-present Board of Trustees, Professor of African American Studies, and Professor of History at Northwestern University
2004-present John A. Hannah Distinguished Professor of American History, Adjunct, Michigan State University
2006 Inducted into the American Academy of Arts and Sciences
In addition to events listed in the chronology, Hine has been an active member of a variety of professional organization, including: American Academy for the Arts and Sciences, Organization of American Historians, Association for the Study of African-American Life and History, Association of Black Women Historians, Southern Association for Women Historians, Southern Historical Association for Women Historians. She has also served on numerous committees and editorial boards such as the Executive Committee for the National Academy for Critical Studies, and the Editorial Board for the Dictionary of American Nurses.
Sources for biographical information include: Darlene Clark Hine website, www.msu.edu/~hined/ and Northwestern University's Department of African American Studies Core Faculty website.
Collection Overview
The Darlene Clark Hine Papers span the dates from about 1879 to 1996, with the bulk of the files dating from the 1970s to 1996. Earlier dates represent reproductions of archival materials, chiefly photographs. Through professional correspondence, research and writings materials, and professional service files, the collection documents the career of Darlene Clark Hine, professor of African American history, college administrator, and published author on African American history in the United States. The collection is arranged into the following series: Correspondence, Personal Files, Professional Service, and Research and Writings. The largest file group in the collection is the Professional Service Series, which documents Hines' extensive involvement with academic organizations and civic organizations, her activities as lecturer and speaker at many conferences, symposia, and other events, and to a lesser extent, her activities at Purdue and Michigan State University as a professor, mentor, and faculty member. The second largest series in the collection, Research and Writings, contains files of research and publication materials related to Hines' major published works, articles, and media projects concerning African American slavery; the Civil Rights movement; African American suffrage, particularly in Texas; race relations in the United States; African American women in the Midwest; and black women in the nursing profession. Items in the Correspondence Series chiefly relate to Hine's academic activities at Purdue, Michigan State, Arizona State, and the University of Delaware, and her publishing activities; there is also some correspondence with foundations concerning funding for projects. Finally, the Personal Files contains such items as Hines' early student work, including her master's thesis, and some correspondence, cards, and photographs. Each series and its subdivisions are described in full in the collection description that follows. Acquired as part of the John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture.
Related Material
Nell Irvin Painter Papers, 1793-2006 and undated, bulk 1876-2004
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Black Women in the Middle West Project Records, 1932-1986
Indiana Historical Society
Primaries -- Texas -- Case studies; Slavery -- United States -- History; United States -- Race relations -- History; African Americans -- Suffrage -- Texas -- History; African American nurses -- History; African American women college administrators; African American women authors -- 20th century; African American women -- Middle West -- History; African American historians -- Correspondence; Hine, Darlene Clark; Purdue University -- Faculty; Michigan State University -- Faculty; John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture
- Correspondence Series, 1977-1994, 4 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains professional correspondence between Hine and her professors, colleagues, and students over the course of her career, and some administrative and interdepartmental memoranda from each of the universities at which Hine served as professor. Correspondence also includes some letters of congratulation, History Department Faculty Speakers Committee correspondence, departmental meeting minutes, correspondence related to commencement addresses, college advisory committee meeting minutes. There are also two groups of correspondence files for Hine's exchanges with publishers and foundations. Records are arranged chronologically with some gaps present.
  - Purdue, 1977 June-1986 Feb., 53 folders (Box 1)
  - Purdue, 1986 Mar.-1989 Mar., 13 folders (Box 2)
  - Michigan State University, 1987 May-1988 Feb., 10 folders (Box 2)
  - Michigan State University, 1988 Mar.-1990 Sept., 28 folders (Box 3)
  - Michigan State University, 1990 Oct.-1994 Dec., 8 folders (Box 4)
  - Arizona State University, 1984-1986 (Box 4)
  - University of Delaware, 1988-1990, 5 folders (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with publishers, 1978-1990
    - 1978, Alfred Knopf (Box 4)
    - 1978, Doubleday and Company (Box 4)
    - 1978, Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, Inc. (Box 4)
    - 1978, Harper and Row Publishers (Box 4)
    - 1978, J.B. Lippincott Company (Box 4)
    - 1978, Little, Brown and Company (Box 4)
    - 1978, MacMillan Company (Box 4)
    - 1978, McGraw-Hill Book Company (Box 4)
    - 1978, New American Library (Box 4)
    - 1978, Pantheon Books (Box 4)
    - 1978, The Dial Press (Box 4)
    - 1978, W.W. Norton and Company, Inc. (Box 4)
    - 1978, William Morrow and Company Inc. (Box 4)
    - 1979, University of Kentucky Press (Box 4)
    - 1979-1980, Kraus-Thomson Organization (Box 4)
    - 1982, Yale University Press (Box 4)
    - 1985, Feminist Press (Box 4)
    - 1985-1987, Garland Press (Box 4)
    - 1985, Greenwood Press (Box 4)
    - 1985-1989, Louisiana State Press, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - 1990, University Press of Kansas (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with foundations, 1987-1990
    - 1987-1998, Ford Foundation (Box 4)
    - 1990, Rockefeller Foundation (Box 4)
- Personal Files Series, 1968-1989, and undated, 2 boxes
  Chiefly materials associated with Hine's years as an undergraduate at Roosevelt University, and as a graduate student at Kent State University. Items include Kent State newsletters, course notes and papers, copy of master's thesis, report on black students' concerns. Other documents included in the student years material include personal correspondence between Hine and her friends, correspondence with her husband, William Hine, photographs, and greeting cards. Arranged in two groups: Course Material and Other Student Material, and within in chronological order.
  - Course Material, 1968-1975 and undated
    - 1968-1970, Examination books (Box 5)
    - 1968-1971, Notes for courses and papers (Box 5)
    - 1968 Feb.-Mar., Course notes, American Diplomacy (Box 5)
    - 1968 Nov., Paper, course on slavery (Box 5)
    - 1969-1970, Course notes and syllabi (Box 5)
    - 1969, Coursework, History 488 and 588 (Box 5)
    - 1969 May, Course paper, American Colonization Society as a social movement (Box 5)
    - 1969 Oct.-Dec., Course notes (Box 5)
    - 1969 Nov., Paper for History of West Africa course (Box 5)
    - 1969 Dec., Paper for Civil War History course (Box 5)
    - 1970 Jan.-1971 Mar., Course notes, Colonial American History (Box 5)
    - 1970 June, Paper, Urban History (Box 5)
    - 1970 July, Paper, Relations between Indians and African Americans (Box 5)
    - 1975 Mar., Blacks and the Second Seminole War, 1835-1838, paper for lecture series (Box 5)
    - Undated, Various notes for papers (Box 5)
    - Undated, Course notes, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Other Student Material, 1968-1989 and undated
    - 1968-1970, Report on black students' concerns (Box 6)
    - 1969 Sept.-1971 May, Notes from textbook, 19th Century American History Course, 4 folders (Box 6)
    - 1970, The Propaganda of the American Colonization Society, 1815-1840, Hine's master's thesis (Box 6)
    - 1972-1989, Personal correspondence, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - 1980, Kent State Ten Years Later (Box 6)
    - Kent University newsletters, 1985-1986, 1989 (Box 6)
    - 1985 Feb., Correspondence on completion of Ph.D. (Box 6)
    - 1985-1989, Correspondence between Darlene Clark Hine and William Hine (Box 6)
    - Undated, Racist flyer (Box 6)
- Professional Service Series, 1971-1995, and undated, 21 boxes
  Divided into three subseries: Organizations; Committees, Advisory, and Editorial Boards; and Speaking Engagements and Conferences. Consists of files relating to Hine's work with African American and historical organizations, conferences she attended, and correspondence related to lectures. Records are typically arranged within subseries in alphabetical order by topic or organization, and within by year. Included are extensive files of correspondence for major organizations such as the American Historical Association (AHA), the Organization of American Historians (OAH), the Association for the Study of African-American Life and History (ASALH), and the Association of Black Women Historians (ABWH). The latter includes letters from Hine to black women historians concerning the establishment of the ABWH. Organization files can include records on membership criteria; the election of officers; formation of committees; materials related to organization newsletters; membership questionnaires and mailing lists; program and awards files; annual reports; and meeting minutes. Other files in this series include information relating to numerous advisory and editorial boards that Hine has served on and information pertaining to conferences and symposia that she has attended.
  - Organizations Subseries
    - American Historical Association (AHA), 1978-1994
      - Legacies of Myths, Distortions and Omissions: A Case for the Teaching of Black History, presented at the Conference on Teaching Afro-American History, 1978 Dec. (Box 7)
      - Conference on Teaching Afro-American History Correspondence, 1978-1984, 19 folders (Box 7)
      - Correspondence, 1981 Mar.-1994 Dec., 37 folders (Box 7)
    - Association for the Study of African-American Life and History (ASALH), 1977-1995
      - Correspondence, 1977 Jan.- 1985 Apr., 50 folders (Box 8)
      - ASALH correspondence, 1986 Jan.- 1995 Nov., 39 folders (Box 9)
      - ASALH conference paper: A Special Mission: Black Lawyers, Suffrage and Social Change 1986 Oct. (Box 9)
      - Reports, 1987 Dec. -1989 Oct., 3 folders (Box 9)
      - Newsletters, 1990-1991 (Box 9)
      - Meeting minutes, 1987 June-1987 Oct., 2 folders (Box 9)
      - Programs, 1971 Oct.- 1990 Oct., 8 folders (Box 9)
    - Association of Black Women Historians (ABWH), 1979-1994
      - Correspondence, 1979 May- 1994 Oct., 22 folders (Box 10)
      - Newsletters, 1979 July-1994, 14 folders (Box 10)
      - Organizational information, 1987 July (Box 10)
      - Programs, 1988 Oct. (Box 10)
      - Reports, 1981 Feb.-1988 July (Box 10)
    - Africana Studies Research Center Advisory Committee correspondence, 1974 Jan.-1984 Feb., 26 folders (Box 11)
    - Black Faculty and Staff Caucus at Purdue University, 1974-1987
      - Black Faculty and Staff Caucus, 1975 Sept.- 1979 Mar., 28 folders (Box 12)
      - Black Cultural Center newsletters 1974 Sept.- 1987 Apr. (Box 12)
    - Joint Center of Political Studies (JCPS), 1970-1990
      - JCPS correspondence, 1989-1990, 2 folders (Box 13)
      - History, 1989, and Undated, 4 folders (Box 13)
      - Reports, 1970-1989, 4 folders (Box 13)
      - Notes, 1989, and Undated, 3 folders (Box 13)
    - National Humanities Center, 1985-1987 (Box 13)
    - Organization of American Historians (OAH), 1978-1995
      - Correspondence, 1978 Jan.-1993 Oct., 63 folders (Box 14)
      - Correspondence, 1993 Nov.-1995 Mar., 10 folders (Box 15)
      - ABWH related correspondence, 1981 Oct.-1983 Nov., 7 folders (Box 15)
      - FISPE related correspondence, 1984 Aug.-1986 Jan. (Box 15)
      - Programs, 1982 Mar.-1990 Mar., 3 folders (Box 15)
      - Reports, 1986 Nov.-1987, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Southern Association of Women Historians (SAWH), 1980-1994
      - SAWH correspondence, 1983 July-1993 Sept., 33 folders (Box 16)
      - SAWH conference paper, Rape and the Inner Lives of Black Women in the Middle West: Preliminary Thoughts on the Culture of Dissemblance, 1988 June 11 (Box 17)
      - Agenda, 1989 Nov. (Box 17)
      - Membership list, 1983 Dec. (Box 17)
      - Newsletters, 1980-1994, 14 folders (Box 17)
      - Program, 1988 (Box 17)
    - Southern Historical Association (SHA), 1966-1991
      - SHA correspondence, 1980 Oct.-1984 Aug., 24 folders (Box 17)
      - SHA correspondence, 1985-Feb.-1988 Aug., 30 folders (Box 18)
      - SHA correspondence, 1988 Sept.-1988 Dec., 4 folders (Box 19)
      - SHA Conference, 1989 Jan.-1989 Dec., 12 folders (Box 19)
      - Participation List, 1966-1989, 2 folders (Box 19)
      - Proposals and sessions, 1989, 2 folders (Box 20)
      - Program committee worksheets, 1989 (Box 20)
      - Programs, 1989, 2 folders (Box 20)
      - Reports, 1989 (Box 20)
    - Other Organizations, 1979-1994
      - Center for Afro-American and African Studies (CAAS), 1987-1990, 2 folders (Box 21)
      - Coordinating Committee on Women in the Historical Profession (CCWHP), 1990-1994, 4 folders (Box 21)
      - Conference Group on Women's History (CGWH), 1979-1994, 5 folders (Box 21)
      - Committee on Institutional Cooperation (CIC), 1989-1994, 3 folders (Box 21)
      - Consortium of Social Science Associations (COSSA),1991-1994, 7 folders (Box 21)
      - Center for Studies of Ethnicity and Race in America (CSERA), 1990-1992, 4 folders (Box 21)
      - National Council for History Education, Inc. (NCHE), 1990-1994, 6 folders (Box 21)
  - Committees, Advisory, and Editorial Boards, 1979-1990
    - African American Triumph Consortium Advisory Board, 1990 (Box 22)
    - Amherst College Visiting Committee for Black Studies, 1987-1988, 2 folders (Box 22)
    - Amistad Research Center Membership Committee, 1987 (Box 22)
    - CIC African American and Africa Diaspora Studies Directors, 1990-1994, 3 folders (Box 22)
    - CIC Summer Institute Committee, 1979-1981, 2 folders (Box 22)
    - Dictionary 20th Century Black Leaders editorial board, 1985-1988, 3 folders (Box 22)
    - The Feminist Press Advisory Board, 1981 (Box 22)
    - Frederick Douglass Papers Project editorial board, 1987 (Box 22)
    - Hampton University review board, 1989 (Box 22)
    - Indiana Committee for the Humanities, 1984 (Box 22)
    - Journal of American Association of University Administrators editorial board, 1983 (Box 22)
    - Journal for Higher Education Management, 1985-1987, 2 folders (Box 22)
    - Journal of Women's History editorial board, 1990 (Box 22)
    - Martin Luther King Jr. Papers Project Advisory Board, 1987 (Box 22)
    - The Medical College of Pennsylvania Advisory Board, 1987 (Box 22)
    - Michigan Women's Historical Center Honors Committee, 1989 (Box 22)
    - National Council for History Education, Inc. Advisory Board, 1990 (Box 22)
    - North Carolina Central University Advisory Board, 1987-1989 (Box 22)
    - Umoja, 1980-1981, 2 folders (Box 22)
    - Women's Studies Quarterly Editorial Board, 1985 (Box 22)
    - Yale University Council Committee on the Graduate School, 1990 (Box 22)
  - Speaking Engagements and Conferences, 1975-1990
    - Presentations for Conferences and Symposia, 1975-1990
      - 1st Scholarly Research Conference on Black Women, 1979 (Box 23)
      - 7th Annual Fall Conference on Nursing History, 1990 (Box 23)
      - Against the Odds Conference, 1984 (Box 23)
      - American Ethnicity Conference, 1975 (Box 23)
      - American Association for History of Medicine, 1983 (Box 23)
      - Association of Social and Behavioral Scientists, Inc. Conference, 1985 (Box 23)
      - Berkshire Conference, 1977-1989, 7 folders (Box 23)
      - Black Experience Workshop, 1987 (Box 23)
      - Booker T. Washington Conference, 1989-1990 (Box 23)
      - Center for Advanced Studies in the Behavioral Sciences, 1990 (Box 23)
      - Center of Philanthropy Conference, 1987 (Box 23)
      - A Century of Women's Health Practices and Practioners Conference, 1985 (Box 23)
      - Christamore House, 1984 (Box 23)
      - CIC Summer Institute in Social Science Annual Conference, 1982 (Box 23)
      - CIC Summer Research Opportunities Program Conference, 1988 (Box 23)
      - Conference on Slavery, Emancipation and Post Emancipation Societies, 1990 (Box 23)
      - Consortium of Social Science Association Annual Meeting, 1990 (Box 23)
      - Discovering Our Hidden Past: Local Afro-American History Conference, 1982 (Box 23)
      - The Dream: Afro-American and Evolution of American Constitution Conference, 1985 (Box 23)
      - Ethnic Studies Conference, 1990 (Box 24)
      - Girls Club of America, 1984 Apr.-1984 Nov., 6 folders (Box 24)
      - Historical Society of Michigan, 1988 (Box 24)
      - Immanuel Presbyterian Church, 1984 (Box 24)
      - Indianapolis Museum of Art, 1982 (Box 24)
      - Indianapolis Recorder Women's Charities, 1984 May (Box 24)
      - Michigan Council for the Humanities, 1990 (Box 24)
      - Missouri Valley History Conference, 1985 Mar. (Box 24)
      - The National Association of Women's Centers Conference, 1986 (Box 24)
      - National Conference on Black Women in America, 1984 (Box 24)
      - National Conference on Black Studies, 1985 (Box 24)
      - National Conference on Local Afro-American History, 1982 (Box 24)
      - National Council for Black Studies Annual Conference, 1985-1987, 3 folders (Box 24)
      - National Council of Negro Women, 1981 (Box 24)
      - National Council for the Social Studies Annual Meeting, 1990 (Box 24)
      - National Women's Studies Association Convention, 1986 (Box 24)
      - Politics of Caring Conference ,1990 (Box 24)
      - Roads, 1990 (Box 24)
      - Symposia for Carnegie Mellon University, 1987 (Box 25)
      - Smithsonian Institution, 1986 Jan. (Box 25)
      - Soundings, 1990 (Box 25)
      - Southern Conference of Afro-American Studies, 1979 (Box 25)
      - Symposium on Contemporary Problems in America, 1987 (Box 25)
      - Symposium for East Carolina University School of Medicine, 1989 (Box 25)
      - Symposium for Indiana University, 1983 (Box 25)
      - Symposium for University of Santa Clara, 1989 (Box 25)
      - Third World Conference, 1982-1989, 6 folders (Box 25)
      - Virginia Foundation for Independent Colleges, 1990 (Box 25)
      - Women's History and Public Policy Conference, 1989 (Box 25)
      - World's Fair Planning Conference, 1985 (Box 25)
      - YMCA, 1990 (Box 25)
    - Presentations Given at Universities and Colleges, 1978-1990
      - Auburn University, 1990 (Box 26)
      - Emory University, 1990 (Box 26)
      - Havard University, 1989-1990 (Box 26)
      - Hunter College, 1990 (Box 26)
      - Illinois State University, 1988 (Box 26)
      - Indiana University, 1984 (Box 26)
      - Indiana University of Pennsylvania, 1987 (Box 26)
      - Metropolitan State College, 1984 (Box 26)
      - Michigan State University, 1988-1990, 3 folders (Box 26)
      - Northern Illinois University, 1986 (Box 26)
      - Purdue University, 1978-1985, and Undated, 10 folders (Box 26)
      - Smith College, 1984 (Box 26)
      - St. Olaf College, 1981 (Box 26)
      - SUNY College at Brackport, 1990 (Box 26)
      - SUNY College at New Paltz, 1990 (Box 26)
      - Syracuse University, 1987-1988, 2 folders (Box 26)
      - Texas Southern University, 1989 (Box 27)
      - University of Delaware, 1990 (Box 27)
      - University of Galway, 1987 (Box 27)
      - University of Georgia, 1981 (Box 27)
      - University of Illinois, Chicago, 1990 (Box 27)
      - University of Illinois, College of Medicine, Peoria, 1986 (Box 27)
      - University of Michigan, 1989 (Box 27)
      - University of Northern Iowa, 1990 (Box 27)
      - University of Pennsylvania, 1990 (Box 27)
      - University of Pittsburg, 1990 (Box 27)
      - University of Texas, Austin, 1982-1988, 2 folders (Box 27)
      - University of Virginia at Charlottesville, 1980 (Box 27)
      - University of Wisconsin, Madison, 1990-1991 (Box 27)
      - Utah State University, 1990 (Box 27)
      - Williams College, 1984 (Box 27)
- Research and Writings Series, circa 1879-1996 and undated, bulk 1950-1996, 14 boxes